Cornelius Chase Family Papers
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress
Cornelius Chase Family Papers 1745-1974 (bulk 1822-1870)
MSS58552
Chase, Cornelius, 1780-1868
3,000 items
7 containers plus 1 oversize
2.8 linear feet
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress Washington, D.C.
Clergyman, educator, and farmer. Correspondence, business and financial papers, subject files, reports, speeches, newspaper clippings, and miscellany relating to various members of the Chase family, especially Cornelius Chase, his son, Cornelius Thurston Chase, and the latter's career as superintendent of public instruction in Florida. Other material concerns the slave trade in Richmond, Virginia, the Confederate Army, and the Reverend Jonas King.
Selected Search Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the LC Catalog. They are grouped by name of person or organization, by subject or location, and by occupation and listed alphabetically.
People
Chase family.; Chase, Cornelius Thurston, 1819-1870. Cornelius Thurston Chase papers. 1835-1953.; Chase, Cornelius, 1780-1868.; King, Jonas, 1792-1869--Correspondence.; Lincoln, Abraham, 1809-1865--Interviews.; Stokes, E. H. (Ellwood Haines), 1815-1897. E.H. Stokes papers. 1846-1865.
Organizations
Browning and Moore Company.; Confederate States of America. Army--Supplies and stores.; Confederate States of America. Army.; Confederate States of America. Army. Confederate States of America. Army records. 1860-1865.; Confederate States of America. Army. Medical Department.; Dickerson, Hill, and Company.; E.H. Stokes, Betts, and Gregory Company.; Florida. Department of Public Instruction.; Moore and Dawson Company.
Subjects
Contracts--Virginia--Richmond.; Education--Florida.; Military deserters--Confederate States of America.; Military hospitals--South Carolina.; Military hospitals--Virginia.; Physicians--Employment--Virginia--Richmond.; Quartermasters--Confederate States of America.; Slave trade--United States.; Slave trade--Virginia--Richmond.
Places
South Carolina--History--Civil War, 1861-1865--Hospitals.; United States--History--Civil War, 1861-1865--Casualties.; United States--History--Civil War, 1861-1865--Hospitals.; United States--History--Civil War, 1861-1865--Medical care.; United States--History--Civil War, 1861-1865--Prisoners and prisons.; Virginia--History--Civil War, 1861-1865--Hospitals.
Occupations
Clergy.; Educators.; Farmers.
Provenance
The papers of the Cornelius Chase Family were given to the Library of Congress by John Terry Chase in 1978 and 1980.
Transfers
Items have been transferred from the Manuscript Division to other custodial divisions of the Library. Prints, photographs, and other visual and graphic materials have been transferred to the Prints and Photographs Division. Some maps have been transferred to the Geography and Map Division. All transfers are identified in these divisions as part of the Cornelius Chase Family Papers.
Access and Restrictions
The papers of the Cornelius Chase Family are open to research. Researchers are advised to contact the Manuscript Reading Room prior to visiting. Many collections are stored off-site and advance notice is needed to retrieve these items for research use.
Scope and Content Note
The papers of the Cornelius Chase Family span the years 1745-1974 with the bulk of the material between 1822 and 1870. The collection consists of family papers, correspondence, a journal, financial material, reports, speeches and writings, genealogical material, drawings, printed matter, and miscellany.
The family papers chiefly reflect the lives of Cornelius Chase (1780-1868) and his son Cornelius Thurston Chase (1819-1870), both of whom were ministers and educators. The collection also features Cornelius Thurston Chase's career as superintendent of public instruction for the state of Florida. Included with the family papers are correspondence and writings of other family members, financial material, and genealogical items.
Also included are records relating to the slave trading activities of E. H. Stokes, Betts and Gregory Company, Browning and Moore Company, Dickerson, Hill, and Company, and Moore and Dawson Company. Material relating to the Confederate States Army consist of documents collected by Cornelius Thurston Chase and includes reports on Confederate hospitals in Virginia and South Carolina, medical contracts with private physicians in Richmond, provision returns, circulars and special orders relating to the Medical Department, lists of deserters, quartermaster reports, reports on prisoners of war and sick and wounded soldiers.
A folder of Jonas King material among the Miscellany includes correspondence and a copy of King's interview with Abraham Lincoln.
Container List
- Confederate States Army (Box 1)
  - Circulars and special orders, 1862-1864, (2 folders) (Box 1)
  - Consolidated provision returns, 1861-1862 (Box 1)
  - Coupon bonds, 1861-1864 (Box 1)
  - List of deserters, 1863 (Box 1)
  - Miscellany, 1862-1865, undated (Box 1)
  - Office of the Medical Director (Box 1)
    - Contracts, 1862-1864, (2 folders) (Box 1)
    - Correspondence (Box 1)
      - 1860, Apr.-1864, Aug., (3 folders) (Box 1)
      - 1864, Sept.-1865, Apr., (2 folders) (Box 2)
    - Reports of the sick and wounded, 1862-1865 See also Oversize (Box 2)
  - Reports (Box 2)
    - Federal prisoners, 1863-1864 (Box 2)
    - Hospital, 1862 (Box 2)
    - Passport office, 1864 (Box 2)
    - Special requisitions, 1862-1863 (Box 2)
- Family Papers (Box 2)
  - Cary, Maria (granddaughter), correspondence, 1864-1890, undated (Box 2)
  - Cary, Mary (granddaughter), correspondence, 1865-1899 (Box 2)
  - Chase, Benjamin (brother), correspondence, 1807-1848 (Box 2)
  - Chase, Benjamin (son), letter, 1856 (Box 2)
  - Chase, Caroline Frances Aitken (daughter-in-law) (Box 2)
    - Correspondence, 1870-1909 (Box 2)
    - Poetry, undated (Box 2)
  - Chase, Cornelius (1780-1868) (Box 2)
    - Biographical data, 1848, undated (Box 2)
    - Correspondence, 1822-1857, undated, (2 folders) (Box 2)
    - Diary fragment, undated (Box 3)
    - Financial and legal documents, 1818-1871, undated (Box 3)
    - "In Remembrance of Cornelius Chase," memorial booklet, undated (Box 3)
    - Poetry, undated (Box 3)
    - Sermons, undated (Box 3)
    - Writings, undated (Box 3)
  - Chase, Cornelius Thurston (1819-1870) (son) (Box 3)
    - Correspondence, 1836-1870, undated, (5 folders) (Box 3)
    - Eulogy, 1870 (Box 3)
    - Financial and legal papers, 1835-1953, undated (Box 3)
    - Miscellany, 1837-1870 (Box 4)
    - Poetry, undated (Box 4)
    - Printed matter, 1868-1872 (Box 4)
    - Writings, undated, (2 folders) (Box 4)
  - Chase, Cornelius T. (grandson) (Box 4)
    - Correspondence, 1897-1907 (Box 4)
    - Funeral service and eulogy, 1944 (Box 4)
  - Chase, Eliza (daughter) (Box 4)
    - Correspondence, 1837-1855, undated (Box 4)
    - Poetry, undated (Box 4)
  - Chase, Jethro (uncle), correspondence, 1820-1821 (Box 4)
  - Chase, Lena Louise Tyler (Mrs. Cornelius T. Chase) (Box 4)
    - Correspondence, 1906-1947 (Box 4)
    - Condolences, 1946-1947 (Box 4)
  - Chase, Lydia C., correspondence, 1917-1929 (Box 4)
  - Chase, Mary M. (daughter), correspondence, 1849-1853, undated (Box 4)
  - Chase, Mehitable (daughter), letter, undated (Box 5)
  - Chase, Stephen (grandfather), correspondence, 1768-1822, undated (Box 5)
  - Chase, T. F. F., correspondence, 1870 (Box 5)
  - Other family members, 1833, 1855-1869, 1974, undated (Box 5)
  - Correspondents other than family members, 1856-1867, undated (Box 5)
  - Miscellany (Box 5)
    - Ancestral register, undated See Oversize (Box 5)
    - Drawings and plans, undated See also Oversize (Box 5)
    - Genealogy, 1847, 1870, undated (Box 5)
    - Legal papers, 1745, 1770, 1810-1834, 1864, undated See also Oversize (Box 5)
    - Poems and other writings, 1862, 1870, undated (Box 5)
    - Receipts, 1862, 1870, undated (Box 5)
- Miscellany (Box 5)
  - American Union Commission, 1865 (Box 5)
  - Arabic letters, circa 1830 (Box 5)
  - Cards and labels, undated (Box 5)
  - Financial papers, 1852, 1861-1865, undated (Box 5)
  - King, Jonas, 1823-1864 (Box 5)
  - Maps and charts, undated (Box 5)
  - Newspaper clippings, 1858-1896, undated (Box 5)
  - Notes, 1864, undated (Box 5)
  - Printed matter, 1832, 1857-1908, undated, (2 folders) (Box 5)
  - Richmond, Va., Mayor's Court, 1845-1855 (Box 6)
  - United States Army Quartermaster Corps, 1867 (Box 6)
  - Writings, undated (Box 6)
- Slave traders (Box 6)
  - Browning and Moore Company, 1853-1862, undated, (2 folders) (Box 6)
  - Dickerson, Hill, and Company, 1855-1862, (2 folders) (Box 6)
  - Miscellany (Box 6)
    - Correspondence, 1855-1863, undated (Box 6)
    - Financial notes and records, 1857-1865, undated (Box 6)
  - Moore and Dawson Company, 1860 (Box 6)
  - Moore, E. C., 1853-1860 (Box 6)
  - Smith and Maddox, 1855-1863 (Box 6)
  - Stokes, E. H. (Box 6)
    - Correspondence (Box 6)
      - 1856-1861 (Box 6)
      - 1863-1865, undated, (3 folders) (Box 7)
    - Financial and business records (Box 7)
      - Account books, 1856-1862 (Box 7)
      - Accounts and receipts, 1846-1865, (4 folders) (Box 7)
      - Canceled checks, 1851-1864 (Box 7)
      - E. H. Stokes, Betts, and Gregory Company (Box 7)
        - Accounts, 1860 (Box 7)
        - Correspondence, 1859-1861, (3 folders) (Box 7)
    - Legal papers, 1860-1864 (Box 7)
- Oversize (Box OV 1)
  - Confederate States Army (Box OV 1)
    - Office of the Medical Director (Box OV 1)
      - Reports of the sick and wounded, 1862-1865 (Container 2) (Box OV 1)
  - Family papers (Box OV 1)
    - Ancestral register, undated (Container 5) (Box OV 1)
    - Drawings and plans, undated (Container 5) (Box OV 1)
    - Legal papers, 1745, 1810-1834, 1864, undated (Container 5) (Box OV 1)